<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An essay for the regvlation of the practice of physick upon which regulation are grounded the composure of all differences between physicians and apothecaries, and reasons for preferring  the long accustomed way of practising by prescription : to which is added a brief discourse concerning arcanas of nostrums ... / by a lover of truth and the good of mankind.</title>
            <author>Lover of truth and the good of mankind.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38625</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3283</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41373</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31355209</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31355209</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110349</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38625)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110349)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1738:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An essay for the regvlation of the practice of physick upon which regulation are grounded the composure of all differences between physicians and apothecaries, and reasons for preferring  the long accustomed way of practising by prescription : to which is added a brief discourse concerning arcanas of nostrums ... / by a lover of truth and the good of mankind.</title>
                  <author>Lover of truth and the good of mankind.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Taylor, bookseller ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained and cropped, with print show-through, and loss of text.</note>
                  <note>"Concerning midwives" : p. 38-40.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medical laws and legislation --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110349:1"/>
            <p>AN ESSAY FOR THE REGVLATION OF THE PRACTICE of PHYSICK. Upon which REGULATION Are grounded The Compoſure of all Differences Between <hi>PHYSICIANS</hi> and <hi>APOTHECARIES:</hi> AND Reaſons for preferring the long accuſtomed Way of Practiſing by Preſcription.</p>
            <p>To which is added A brief Diſcourſe concerning <hi>ARCANAS</hi> or <hi>NOSTRUMS,</hi> and another of the Deportment of Phyſicians towards the Sick, and one another: as alſo of the Apothecaries to the Sick, to Phyſicians, and to Members of their own Society.</p>
            <p>By a Lover of Truth and the Good of Mankind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Taylor</hi> Bookſeller, at the Sign of the <hi>Hand</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> on <hi>London Bridge.</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:110349:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110349:2"/>
            <head>AN ESSAY FOR THE Regulation OF THE <hi>PRACTICE</hi> of <hi>PHYSICK.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Uch hath been writ to widen Differences between Doctors and Apothecaries, and to make them irreconcileable one to the other, as if upon that breach depended the better Being and Health of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the Improvement of the Art of Phyſick.</p>
            <p>This has been propagated by ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly, by others incautelouſly: by the firſt becauſe thereby is gained a liberty or convenience in practiſing an Art, in which, as they have a very incompetent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110349:3"/>of Skill, ſo for the exerciſe thereof they have no legal, or a very queſtionable, authority, and therefore are concerned, to keep this Conteſt on foot, under whoſe Umbrage they ſhelter their intruſion, and continue confidently their illicite practice.</p>
            <p>Others incautelouſly, upon injuries received, ſome bold af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts offered, their Profeſſion againſt Law, and Ties of Gratitude invaded: from the ſenſe and provocation of which wrongs, they have too ſuddenly preferred the ruine and extirpation of a Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, eſtabliſhed by the ſame Authority with themſelves, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable for Numbers, for bearing a ſhare in the publick Charge; and very many of them eminently knowing and sk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lful in their Profeſſion; before ſuch prudent endeavours, as might have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced all to a juſt and regular eſtabliſhment, contentful to both Faculties, and much conducing to the publick weal and accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the People.</p>
            <p>That there ſhould be a neceſſity of the ruine of one or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as ſome have ſuppoſed, is indeed ſuppoſed by ſuch as are F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iends to neither, but as the Devil perſuades men in deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that there is now no room left for repentance: So theſe would perſwade both, that <hi>huc tandem deventum eſt,</hi> 'tis in vain to think of a Compoſure now, both parties have criminated and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criminated, and ſo highly incenſed one another, that there is no hope left to bring things to a due regulation, juſt bounds and ſubordination.</p>
            <p>To obviate which purpoſe is the intention of this Paper, by propoſing ſuch a way of eſtabliſhment as may afford full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to the Reaſonable of both Profeſſions, may give the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian a full inſight into all the parts of Pharmacy, both in the knowledg of all Drugs, as alſo in the beſt ways of working upon them; and yet ſo as not to take up too much of his time from requiring knowledg in other as neceſſary parts of Phyſick. To keep the Apothecaries within the Verge of their own Profeſſion, upon the operative parts of which their time being wholly ſpent, they become very aſſiſtant to the Phyſician in his Improvements of Medicine. To provide in the beſt manner for the people, that their Medicines may be good, ſound, efficacious, accoording to the preſcript of the Phyſician; by means whereof they may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with confidence and good expectation by the Patient, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110349:3"/>ſecure che mind of the Phyſician, that his orders are well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
            <p>In doing whereof, it is not to be ſuppoſed, that any thing can be offered in this or the exerciſe of any other Art, that ſhall be wholly free from hazard, or not liable to objections in the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution; no affair in the world is exempted from it; it is not therefore amply ſufficient, that ſuch a way be propoſed as is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the feweſt exceptions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and thoſe of ſmalleſt moment, and (which is moſt comprehenſive of the main ends) by all to be aim'd at, the beſt proviſion for the peoples Health, and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of the Pharmaceutick part of Phyſick.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Apothecaries, by their Maſter, Warden; and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants, ſolemnly promiſe, not to pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iſe Phyſick, except in caſe of abſolute neceſſity, but to keep to their proper buſineſs of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, diſpenſing and vending Medicines.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Company of Apothecaries do oblige their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, already admitted, and to be admitted, not to practiſe Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick: and in caſe they do ſo practiſe, to be liable to ſuch fines and penalties as the Maſter and Wardens, for the time being, ſhall in ſuch caſe eſtabliſh:</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Colledg and Company of Apothecaries joyn to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, in procuring, by their joint intereſt, ſuch Supplements to their ſeveral Charters, as our preſent ſtate of affairs ſhall require, to ſecure to each of them their ſeveral Profeſſions, ſo far forth as the Common liberty and the Laws of the Land will allow.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That ſuch Apothecaries as, notwithſtanding the foreſaid Agreement, ſhall of themſelves practiſe Phyſick, complaint, and juſt proof thereof being firſt made before the Colledg, ſhall, for their firſt time ſo doing, be warn'd thereof by the Colledge, and alſo by the Maſter and Wardens of the Apothecaries Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and be admoniſhed to forbear the ſame for the future: and in caſe they ſhall, notwithſtanding, perſiſt ſo to practiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that then, upon proof made as aforeſaid, they ſhall be declared by the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, at a general meeting, to be practiſing Apothecaries; and the ſeveral members of the Colledg commanded, upon penalty of a fine, to be then declared, not to ſend their Bills to them, or to have to do with them in their Practice, but to leave them to themſelves; as incorrigible intruders into other mens Profeſſions.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:110349:4"/>
            <p n="5">5. That the Members of the Society of Apothecaries ſhall bear themſelves with all due reſpect and ſubordination to the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Colledg of Phyſicians; and that the Members of the Colledg wall have a fair and candid regard to Apothecaries, as to perſons to whom they have entruſted (under their inſpection) ſome moyety of the Manual parts of their Art, and that they both of them unite together, and hold a neceſſary correſpondency for advancement of theſe two Ends;
<list>
                  <item>1. The improvement of Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, and</item>
                  <item>2. the real promotion of the Peoples preſervation, and alſo ſafe and ſpeedy reſtauration from their Diſeaſes.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. That, for the better regulation and execution of this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual part of Phyſick, a view be quarterly made of the Medicines and Drugs of the Apothecaries, or oftner, as need ſhall require, by the Fellows of the Colledg, choſen thereunto, according to the conveniency of their ſeveral Habitations, the ſaid Fellows, in caſe they find things faulty, to give an account thereof to the Cenſors of the Colledg, that by them ſuch juſt and lawful means may be uſed for puniſhment of what is paſt, and prevention of future miſcarriages as their Charter in that caſe providing ſhall thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to authorize them. And that the ſaid Fellows in their ſeveral Diviſions ſhall, as far as other buſineſs will permit, be preſent, not only at the making of thoſe general Remedies, <hi>viz. Mithri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date, Diaſcordium, Venice</hi> and <hi>London Treacle;</hi> but of all others alſo; whereby the Apothecary may be aſſiſted, negligence and frauds prevented; and the Phyſician conſtantly exerciſed in the Manual part, and thereby alſo enabled to ampl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fie, correct and improve this ſo neceſſary and conſiderable part of his Art, not only by his Obſervations made, upon theſe manual proceſſes, but by drawing in all advantages from Philoſophy, his own Reading and Contemplation.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That the Diſpenſatory be reviſed by the Fellows of the Colledg, and republiſhed with ſuch Alterations and Amendmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> as they ſhall judg requiſite: in doing whereof, as a fair regard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to be had to predeceſſors, not to vary without juſt cauſe, ſo are they on the other hand principally to ſteer themſelves, by the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter probability of promoting common good, and producing ſuch Medicines, as may, with great certainty, effect the intentions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by them. For though the preſent <hi>London Diſpenſatory</hi> be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110349:4"/>acknowledged to be the beſt now extant in any part of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and not only to excell the <hi>Auguſtane,</hi> but in many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, its very amendments in the Annotations of <hi>Swelfer:</hi> yet inaſmuch as Pharmacy has been theſe late years much improved by the great induſtry of Collegiates, eſpecially by their own ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual operations, whereby many Diſcoveries have been made, of great improvement to Medicine, and benefit to the Sick: it may eaſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y be concluded, that it is a work of great neceſſity, to make a new Directory to Apothecaries, leaving out very many Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines that are ſuperfluous; correcting what may with little al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration be retained, adding ſuch as are rationally compoſed, and which by much tryal and experience are approved: that ſo this new Diſpenſatory may not be clogg'd with too great a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Medicines, nor with ſuch as may not, for ſome conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable time, without dammage be preſerved, and yet ſupplyed with ſuch an <hi>armamentarium Medicum,</hi> as may moſt hopefully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form all the juſt Indications in the method of Cure, both gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and particular: By the doing whereof the Phyſicians of this Nation will be deſervedly honoured both at home and abroad, the Apothecaries Shops not uſeleſsly incumbred, the beſt provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion made for the Peoples Infirmities.</p>
            <p>Thus may the moſt conſiderable objections be anſwered againſt the preſent method of Practiſe, which have only force from the defect of ſome neceſſary proviſions, which may hereby (and by other ſuggeſtions from Phyſicians of greater abilities) be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed: This being intended but as an Eſſay towards ſuch a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement and Regulation as is clearly wanting; whereby alſo may be prevented that ruine to either Phyſicians or Apothecaries, which by ſome is vainly ſuppoſed to be unavoidable: Confuſion and great diſorder is often, and always ought to be the produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of Order; when prudent men diſcovering the defects and inconveniences of what is irregular, and the artifices of ſuch as deſign, out of private concernment to keep it ſo, do ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to contrive ſuch expedients, as may preſerve all juſt Rights and Intereſts, and endeavour the eſtabliſhment of an Art ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry as Phyſick, from running out into confuſion, where e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man may, without controll, do what he pleaſes, which is not allowable in any other Trade or Faculty whatſoever. The
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110349:5"/>firſt intention of making a Diſpenſatory, was to bring Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines to ſome certainty, that Apothecaries might have a known Rule to make their Medicines by, and not fluctuate and be left a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> liberty to make them by the uncertain guide of many and forreign Diſpenſatories, and the Phyſicians alſo, not left doubtful of their Medicines, as not knowing by what rule the Apothecaries would make them: And this was done by the Colledg, at the intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and command of King <hi>James,</hi> in the year 1618 Some years after a diſcovery being made of ſome defects therein, the Colledg thought fit to give a timely ſtop thereunto, by publiſhing a new Diſpenſatory then ſo called, which they did in the year 1618. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing then hinders, but that upon a greater acquiſition of knowledg, the preſent Colledg (whoſe Members, by many inſtances have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved themſelves not to have neglected the advantages of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, but rather abundantly to have imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oved them) may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce their Diſpenſatory alſo; in many things exceeding the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, as that did what was firſt publiſhed, by how much their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage is greater both in coming after them, and not contenting themſelves with a bare traditional Knowledg, but moſt of them perſonally and practically exerciſing themſelves in the production of Medicines, and gaining thereby thoſe diſcoveries, which Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing meerly notional and bookiſh could never attain unto. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by approving themſelves to be truly ſtudious of publick good, and as well in this as in other parts of their Art, to bring to light, whatſoever upon ſerious deliberation they conceive may promote the ſame.</p>
            <p>If then a new Diſpenſatory were now made, and the other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars above mentioned effected, it would give general ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to the People, anſwer the Scruples of doubtful, and obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the artifices of crafty men, who deſign to diſturb the whole Faculty, to divide not only Phyſicians and Apothecaries, but the Members of the Colledg themſelves, that amidſt ſuch a Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion they may catch at a ſhare of buſineſs, which their own abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, nor the regular way of Pract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce does entitle them to.</p>
            <p>Phyſicians making their own Medicines declining the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries, and uſing them only in their Practice, has had, as all other Novelties, a ſpecious reception, but time diſcovers many inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences that could not be foreſeen: and the moſt prudent Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110349:5"/>though they do not decline making of Medicines, for their own ſatisfaction, yet do much decline that way of Practiſe:</p>
            <p>If Phyſick were now in its firſt dawn and infancy, to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in the world, (before alſo Luxury and Intemperance had multiplyed Diſeaſes, and increaſed the number of Practitioners, and before thoſe Regulations in its practice were by our prudent Anceſtors eſtabliſhed) all that applyed themſelves to this Art, muſt neceſſarily fall into that way of making Medicines themſelves, but the caſe is now far otherwiſe, and therefore they are much beſide the matter; who handle this Queſtion without due conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of its ſtate, as it is now conſtituted. Where firſt,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Violence is offered to the Laws and Orders in being for its preſent Regulation, which doubtleſs were made not without ſerious deliberation and wiſe foreſight of inconveniences, and therefore thoſe who would innovate in this particular, may well be ſuppoſed either to deſign for themſelves, or that they have not ſo fully conſidered the matter as they ought to have done.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſee not with what juſtice they can paſs over the ruine of 7 or 800 perſons and their Wives and Children, the Apothecaries, I mean, who are eſtabliſhed by Law, who make up no inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Company of the City of <hi>London,</hi> bear a ſhare in all publick Charges, and who may vie with the Apothecaries of any part of Chriſtendom, for ſolid Skill in their Profeſſion, who alſo, from the encouragement the Law hath given them, have declined all other way of livelyhood, and depend only upon this for the maintenance of themſelves and Families: To ſtrike at the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of ſuch a ſociety, is, I ſay, very inconſiſtent with the rules of Juſtice and common Charity, which ought to be viſible in all the purpoſes of mankind.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That Medicines ſhould be better made by Phyſicians, than Apothecaries is not likely, it being not barely the Theory that enables thereunto; the one has ſerved ſeven years Apprentice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and been daily employed upon the operative part: the the other from a ſpeculative knowledg confidently thruſt, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelt upon that which he finds much different from the Notions and Ideas thereof he had comprehended in his mind: The one makes it his ſole and only buſineſs to make Medicines, to the other it is but a ſmall part of his Employment, he having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110349:6"/>many and intricate parts of Study; as namely, the Phyſiolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical, Anatomical, Pathological, and Therapeutick part of his Art, each of which are very comprehenſive, and therefore it muſt be preſumed, that either he cannot give full time to buy ſelect Drugs, and make Medicines enough to furniſh the whole of his Practice, eſpecially if it grows to be any thing conſiderable, or that otherwiſe he muſt neglect other parts of his Art equally ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary with that of Pharmacy, either of which are of ill conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to the Sick. Hence, I ſuppoſe, it was, that our Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, foreſeeing this inconvenience, did entruſt this part of their buſineſs to Servants, who afterwards, growing skilful and numerous, were incorporated for the better regulation of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, and grew up by degrees to the Port they are now at: yet were the Phyſicians ſo prudent as to be the Dictators to them, and frequent Inſpectors of their Operations, and Searchers of their Shops, that ſo they might be the better aſcertain'd of their faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diſpenſing and making their Medicines: Which cuſtom being tetianed and faithfully diſcharged, according to the method be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore adviſed, would very much prevent overſights and frauds, and give the Phyſician opportunity of improving Pharmacy, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king obſervations and concluſions from the proceſs of Medicines. All which notwithſtanding he retains his liberty to make Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines at his pleaſure, either at home, or to be preſent whilſt they are made by his order at the Shops of Apothecaries, which is much the ſame thing; ſo that as to the improvement of his Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg full reſpect is had in this method, without other inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, which is an anſwer to the grand objection that ſeems to bear moſt weight for Phyſicians making their own Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines.</p>
            <p n="4">4 It is alſo plauſibly urg'd, that now Phiſicians are forced to truſt Apothecaries, and that their whole Cure depends upon his fidelity: whereas in the other way the Phyſician is ſure of his Medicines, they being made with his own hands.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, that it is all one if they are faithfully and truly made by the hands of other men, who have good skill to make them. In the matter of Fidelity, the defect may be in the want of ſuch an eſtabliſhment as is mentioned; where, if the Phyſician were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times authoritatively preſent, and more often friendly, as a neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110349:6"/>or as having a mutual relation &amp; correſpondency in the art, there would be little ground left for ſuch ſuſpicions. Beſides the Apothecary is concern'd to be faithful both in point of Profit and of Reputation, which are obligations of no ſmall moment, nor have we reaſon to judg but that the Tie of Conſcience is of equal force with them as with other men: In point, I ſay, of Reputation and Profit; for they are apparently hazzarded in making bad Medicines, when the Phyſician comes to view and taſt the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, and finds it another thing than he preſcribed, his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereby fruſtrated, his Cure retarded, his opportunity loſt, his own credit at ſtake; how can he chuſe but lay the fault where it is, and place the Saddle upon the right Horſe; and if through the Apothecaries default ſuch a thing ſhould happen, how would it ſpread? what prejudice would it do him? He would be in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of looſing not only this but other Cuſtomers alſo, to his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great dammage and diſrepute. This the Apothecary very well knows, and therefore is as much concerned as the Phyſician can be, that it may be ſaid, that he has made his Medicines well, diſcharg'd his duty faithfully, whereby he not only fixes that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily he then deals withal, but probably gains thereby ſeveral others alſo.</p>
            <p>If you will ſuppoſe men wretchleſs, and to have no Conſcience, 'tis a weak reflexion, and can no more be charged upon Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries than any other ſort of men: There are good and bad in all Profeſſions: Here are, however, conſiderable engagements upon the Apothecary, and the miſcarriages and overſights, not to ſay unfaithfulneſſes, may more probably be found in thoſe who diſpenſe their own Medicines, where there is no body to overſee or judg them than in thoſe who have others, and thoſe perſons able and concerned, to inſpect what they do.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If it be urg'd that Apothecaries, engaging in Practice, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the making of Medicines, and truſt much to their Servants, whereby overſights are oftentimes committed of no ſmall hazzard to the Sick: I anſwer, that the Objection is very conſiderable, and is no other ways to be anſwered, than by eſtabliſhing ſuch a Regulation as is above mentioned, where Apothecaries are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to their particular buſineſs of making Medicines: But
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110349:7"/>then on the other hand, the objection is much more cogent againſt Phyſicians, eſpecially thoſe who have daily and competent buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for having his Patients to viſit abroad, and they to viſit him at home, having his Studies likewiſe to attend, how is it poſſible he ſhould give time to the making of Medicines; which requires much attendance and conſequently begets a neceſſity of leaving much to the care of his Servants, and that not only in the making but in the diſpenſing of his Medicines; whereas the Apothecary, reduced to his particular Occupation, would have nothing elſe to do but to attend the buſineſs of his Shop, and ſo more hopeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prevent the inconvenience urg'd in the Objection.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It may be urg'd, in the ſixth place, that Phyſicians in buſineſs making their own Medicines, muſt neceſſarily keep ſeveral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, which being bred up in making Medicines, and being apt, as being converſant in Phyſick, to read Phyſick Books, there will ariſe a new ſtock of out-of-courſe Practitioners, which in little time will be exceeding numerous: almoſt all mankind when they grow up toward mans eſtate, think of living in the world, of marrying and having a Family, theſe then having no other way of maintenance, thruſt themſelves upon the practice of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick; and venture, from the impulſe of neceſſity, to attempt any thing that offers it ſelf, which they will with more c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence do from the Reputation of living, and being bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> up, as they will ſay, under ſuch a Doctor. By means whereof the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of indirect Practitioners (who ſwarm too much already) would increaſe to a vaſt bulk, Phyſicians of great Pract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce being, in this way, forc'd to keep many Servants, which would ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly overſtock a Profeſſion that is too much overcharged alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and which is now the general complaint of all that relate to it.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Conſultations, which are often neceſſary, and deſired by the Sick and their Friends, cannot ſo well be managed in this way, as in what is already eſtabliſh'd: unleſs there coald be ſuppoſed a willingneſs in all Phyſicians to communicate their <hi>Noſtrums,</hi> as they are call'd, to every Phyſician they are to conſult withal. For who will give his conſent to the uſe of that be does not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand? or practiſe by an implicit faith? It is not to be ſuppoſed that Phyſicians ſhould always meet with thoſe who are in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110349:7"/>friendſhips and unions, or that all have that communicative ſpirit to impart, what they have with great labour acquired, to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one, eſpecially where they think there will not be a Retri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution.</p>
            <p>Theſe and many other inconveniences there are in this way of Practice, which cannot at firſt view be foreſeen, but may well be preſumed to be the motives that made thoſe who have gone before us to reduce the method of Practice into the way 'tis now in: Nor is their wiſdom to be ſlighted as not done upon good and praiſe worthy grounds: They did think it likewiſe neceſſary to reduce Medicines to ſome reaſonable bounds, which elſe would ſwell to an infinite bulk, leaving a liberty, however, to the Studies of men to ſuperadd what they could find more effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious, to anſwer known intentions, or to obviate new occurring Diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>Here I purpoſed to end, for long Diſcourſes are irkſom both to the Author and Reader: The multitude of Books conſidered, every man ſhould make a conſcience of further peſtering the world with more, unleſs they can produce ſomething new and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to mankind: Some things however I have thought neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be ſuperadded, the preſent poſture of affairs conſidered, which may conduce ſomewhat to the main ſcope of Reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Settlement: I ſhall therefore ſubjoyn ſome Sentiments briefly, upon theſe Subjects, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Arcana</hi>'s or <hi>Noſtrums;</hi> of the ancient and becoming Deportment of Phyſicians, of the decent Carriage of Apotheceries towards the Sick, towards Phyſicians, and alſo towards the members of their own Fraternity. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing I mean to ſubjoyn concerning the Practice of Midwiſery, and ſo to conclude.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>1. Of Arcana's, or Noſtrums.</head>
               <p>Such are Medicines either by great Induſtry and manual expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment found out, traditionally delivered, or collected out of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, not common, and by frequent uſe approved: All of theſe may be called in a large ſence <hi>Arcana,</hi> but the firſt only are properly <hi>Noſtrums,</hi> as being of each Phyſicians own Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:110349:8"/>
               <p>He who ſaid his <hi>Noſtrum</hi> was his Knowledge in the patholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical part of Phyſick, and in a good method of Curing, ſpake certainly much to the purpoſe in this particular: For fince there is ſo great variety of Diſeaſes and their ſymptomes, and theſe ſometimes of great reſemblance one to the other, and yet in their nature very different, and conſequently requiring a differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing method of Cure; ſince alſo they are often of nice and intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate complication; and yet the one requiring preference and priority in Cure; The principal hinge of Practice depends upon accurateneſs in diſtinguiſhing Diſeaſes, where there is ſo great likeneſs, in well underſtanding and weighing the complication, and in a prudent and ſagacious concluſion of what is firſt to be done, eſpecially where there are apparent contraindications. That it is neceſſary every Phyſician ſhould have the knowledg of good and effectual Medicines, that may anſwer every Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, eſpecially ſuch as are generally occurring in practice, is not to be denied: but to averr, that the main ſtreſs of his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs depends upon them, is as if we ſhould account the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of a Carpenter to conſiſt in the goodneſs of his Tools, which every one is to have, and not in his Skill to model, draw forth and contrive Platforms of his Work, and in his ability to effect in good ſort, what he hath ſo modell'd and contrived: So in Phyſick every part of the Art is neceſſary, though the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg in the variety and nature of Diſeaſes, and in a true method of Curing them, may juſtly have priority and preeminence, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more copious and intricate; and which do therefore give the greater value and eſteem to Phyſicians, becauſe from them do flow his more conſtant and more certain ſucceſſes, by which chiefly the people have reaſon to make their Concluſions.</p>
               <p>In conſideration of the neceſſity of Skill in all the parts of Phyſick, to make a compleat Phyſician, and conſequently the difficulty in the acquiſition thereof, it requiring, beſides a good <hi>Indoles,</hi> and natural inclination thereunto, great Learning, fit place and conveniency for Study, Time well employed therein from youth upward, and great Induſtry: as the good <hi>Hippocrates</hi> hath ſuggeſted, upon conſideration whereof, I ſay, Phyſicians of beſt note and ability, have not thought their Art ſo expoſable to popular invaſion, as to judg their Reputation concerned in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110349:8"/>of Medicines, but rather ſwayd by a common regard to the good of mankind, and a deſire to profit and improve their Brethren of the Profeſſion, have been very forward to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate their Knowledg in all parts of Phyſick, knowing well that Life is ſhort enough to acquire requiſice Skill in ſo noble and copious an Art: and though, different from this antient candour in Phyſicians, ſome, who boaſt themſelves to have gained more than ordinary ability, eſpecially ſome of the more preciſely Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical way, and of Wits as volatile as their beloved Mercury; have either communicated little, or in ſuch canting terms of their own invention, the common artifice of arrogance and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, as amounts almoſt to a concealment: yet do I not hence judg that ſuch reſervation is from any ſuperexcellence in their Medicines ſo conceal'd; for that would appear from the note and frequency of ther Cures, the contrary whereunto, by much obſeavation, can be abundantly inſtanced, but rather from the neceſſity of ſuch reſervation, that being the principal Baſis up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which they build their deſired Fame, (for what is not known may be boaſted at pleaſure, and what is known may as eaſily be vilified) That indeed which has begot the neceſſity of ſome Reſervations, contrary to the cuſtom of former Phyſicians, is the ill uſe that is made by Apothecaries of their publication: who aiming at Practice, and putting their ſickle into others Corn, invading our Art, injuriouſly reap the fruit of other mens labour. This is one conſequence of that irregularity things now ſtand in, which by a ſettlement may be remedied; when Phyſicians ſhall have encouragement to communicate what by their Study and manual labour they can produce for common good, being aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd that they may truſt the ſame to Apothecaries, without being abuſed in the irregular uſe thereof, to their ſo great and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent detriment.</p>
               <p>For in this way of ſettlement, as there will not ariſe any reſtraint upon Phyſicians productions, they being at full liberty either to make Medicines themſelves at home, or to overſee and put too their helping hand at the Shops of Apothecaries (which is far from being any diſhonour to them) ſo will the candor, in gennity and liberal Education of a Phyſician oblige him to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear making any unhandſom profit of Medicines: either by enhan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110349:9"/>their prices, or by unworthily conſederating with Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries; but matters being compoſed, to let the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry have them either as an encouragement to his Fidelity, or at ſuch reaſonable rates not exceeding the coſt of the Ingredients and the charge of making them: ſince the Phyſician will be well recompenced by the Reputation of an excellent Medicine of his own invention, his cuſtomary Fees alſo keeping him from having the need of ſuch mean traffick: and likewiſe concerned in point of Reputation to lay an injunction upon the Apothecary, he has ſo gratified, not to deſign more than a competent and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable profit, whether he vends his Medicine to Patient or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary: that ſo it may to all appear, that the Phyſician has no other end in the pains he has taken in producing ſuch Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na's then improving his Art, and providing the beſt Medicines he poſſibly can invent, for the curing of the moſt contumacious and turbulent Diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>I may end this Paragraph <hi>de Arcanis,</hi> with what the prudent <hi>Septalius</hi> ſuggeſts <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>Animadverſione</hi> 14. in theſe words: <hi>As it becomes a Phyſician to have always in readinefs choice and tryed Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, confirmed by frequent experience: yet it does not become him ſo to reſerve them his</hi> Arcana, <hi>as not to be willing to communicate them to others alſo.</hi> I may add that a real and very conſiderable benefit redounds thence to himſelf, ſince thereby inviting others to the ſame promptneſs of communication, every one of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety ſo qualified, is furniſhed not only with his own inventions, but the products and effects of others labours, to the no ſmall improvement of Knowledg, and benefit of the Sick. Not does any thing conduce more to the Honour of a Colledg, or the improvement of an Art, than ſuch a candid communication, and participation of one anothers Knowledg, an Argument that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry member thereof, beſides his own concernment, has a fair regard to his great and principal end, the welfare of the People, a juſt reſpect to his Collegues, and in order to theſe a noble deſign of clearing what is dubious, and ſupplying what is defective in his art.</p>
               <p>In purſuance whereof it is to be ſubjoyned, that as there is no better means to improve Phyſick to a greater degree of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, than by the united endeavours of every member of the Society, ſo is there no Society whatſoever, in <hi>England,</hi> in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110349:9"/>the capacity of ſuch an Improvement as the Colledg of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians.</p>
               <p>As to the firſt, though many things very conſiderable have, to the honour of this Nation, been brought to light, by particular members of the Colledg, ſo well known, as that neither the ſubjects, nor the perſons need to be enumerated: yet is it to be ſuppoſed, that thoſe perſons have in their productions taken to their aſſiſtance, ſome of their more intimate aſſociates, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in Anatomy, where moſt has been done, and where the ſingle endeavours of one man, without aſſiſtance can effect little: Yet may it well be preſumed, that the improvements had been, and might yet be, abundantly more; and that in all parts of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, had or would the Colledg make it their buſineſs, to ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the members thereof into ſeveral Claſſes, diſpoſing to each of them ſuch parts of the Art as their particular Genius, and bent of Study, did encline them to: By means whereof every head and every hand would be at work, and accounts might at fit times be rendred to the whole Society, and this fettled upon much the ſame rules as have been with great judgment invented, and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the eſtabliſhment and continuance of the Royal Society: With this univerſal Rule, ſuperadded, that as the great and noble End of the Colledg, is, the Conſervation of human Life and its reſtauration, when endangered by Sickneſs, ſo ſhould they, as perſons worthy of ſuch an undertaking, decline and diſcourage all nice, uſeleſs and ſuperfluous Subjects, fixing themſelves only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch particulars as have an apparent tendency to the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of ſo excellent an End.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I have ſaid that there is no Society in <hi>England</hi> ſo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of improving the Art, as the Kings Colledg of Phyſicians. There are none that can pretend to any competition, but the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities and the Royal Society.</p>
               <p>As to the firſt, I humbly conceive, that they are in no ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity: 1. as being the moſt of them young men, and therefore wanting that which evinces the certainty and eſtabliſhment of Knowledg, frequent experience. Study and the Learning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by acquired is a good induction and preparation to Knowledg, but without long practiſe, which very few in the Univerſities are capable of; and obſervations skilfully and carefully made there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110349:10"/>neither eminent natural parts, nor the aſſiſtance of the beſt Libraries can produce more than common Notions, which have been 1000 times printed and reprinted, and which, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up the precious time of young Students, have made them loſe thoſe advantages and profitable productions, which the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant exerciſe of their own underſtandings and aſſiduous practice would have exerted from them. But in the main, want of years and continuance in practice are an undeniable diſadvantage to the Phyſicians of the Univerſities, and which cannot be ſaid of moſt of the members of the Colledg.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though the Univerſities have frequent Phyſick Exerciſes, the beſt Libraries, ſolemn Diſſections, a good Phyſick Garden, and a few eminent Practitioners, yet though theſe be allowed, as good preparatory helps to bring a Phyſician into the world, to qualifie and initiate him for Practiſe (eſpecially being firſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the ſociety of other long experienced Phyſicians, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a view and attendance upon their Practice, a thing much wanting and very deſirable in <hi>England,</hi> as of ſingular uſe both to young Phyſicians and to the Sick;) yet as to the great propagations and improvements of the Art, there is abſolutely neceſſary (beſides long experience) a union, incorporation, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent aſſociation and communication, which, as it is wanting in the Univerſities, ſo is it well eſtabliſhed in the Colledg of <hi>London,</hi> and I doubt not but when reſtauration is made of what the Fire conſumed, it will evidently appear by thoſe deſignments, which are as yet but in Embryo, that in the improvement of every part of Phyſick, ſuch earneſt and prudent endeavours will be uſed, as ſhall well ſatisfie the world, that nothing can well be expected, or hoped for, in the Medicinal Art, but will in juſt and competent time be by them effected.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As to the Royal Society, their ends being more general and diffuſive as aiming at the improvement of univerſal knowledg; they are rather adapted and qualified for the advance and perfection of the Mathematicks and Mechanicks than of Phyſick; and ſuch have moſt of their Productions been: and though there may be many Phyſicians amongſt them, however few compared to the reſt; yet are theſe Phyſicians, in juſtice and prime eſtabliſhment, rather ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to honour their own Society, with what they ſhall produce
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110349:10"/>in Phyſick, and being of chief note in the Colledg, rather to uſe their intereſt, that it may be ſo ſettled, that all the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in Phyſick may be placed upon the account of that Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And it ſeems to be ſome ingratitude placed upon that Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of which they were firſt members, not to have uſed their utmoſt endeavours for ſuch a Settlement as may bring to paſs thoſe worthy ends in their own Colledg they would patronize in this other Eſtabliſhment: beſides there are in the Colledg, and belonging to the Members thereof, ſome things which cannot be ſaid of the Royal Society: as
<list>
                     <item>1. that all the members thereof are principally, if not ſolely, devoted to the Study &amp; improvement of Phyſick.</item>
                     <item>2. There is to be conſidered, that the uſe that might be made of the Hoſpitals, which are under the Care of Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Colledg.</item>
                     <item>3. That the Phyſicians in the Colledg, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more numerous, are in better capacity of being ſo divided and taxed with ſeveral Charges in Phyſick, as to comprehend all its parts: and laſtly, the occurrences extraordinary in Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice muſt of neceſſity be much more numerous, than when the number does not riſe to a fifth part, were the Colledge ſo eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed as to oblige all the members to give juſt and frequent accounts of the ſame.</item>
                  </list> This is not ſpoken with any derogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Honour and Ends of that Royal Society, but to evince the Reputation of the more antient Foundation of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, to retrive into themſelves one of the great works and chiefeſt ends of their Eſtabliſhment, in which the Royal Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty may be collateral, and fairly aſſiſtant, but not principal.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the antient and becoming Deportment of Phyſicians.</head>
               <p>I conſider it either in reference to the Sick, or to one another. My purpoſe is not here to comprehend all the particulars that concern the regular carriage and behaviour of Phyſicians, that having been plentifully done in ſeveral Authors of good note, but only to take notice of ſome few particulars of greateſt moment, to the good of the Sick and to the Reputation of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Then it is juſt, that the Phyſician ſhould have in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the Health or Reſtauration of his Patient, as what is moſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110349:11"/>his duty, and what being really implanted in his mind, will make him very intent upon all his occaſions, and in reaſonable time a great proficient in his Art: in order to which it is expedient, that he keep a Regiſter of all the remarkable occurrences of his Practice, and as well his own defects and failings as his appoſite practice and good ſucceſſes: For by the one he will be warned for the future to avoid any precedent miſtake, by the other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive great hints and information of what in like caſes is to be intended: uſing his beſt reaſon to conſider and diſtinguiſh the variety of Bodies, ſymptoms and other circumſtances. As to his profit let it come in, <hi>ſua ſponte,</hi> he need not be ſolicitous about it, for whoſoever does faithfully and conſcientiouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the main, <hi>viz.</hi> the Recovery of his Patient, can never want encouragement ſufficient to recompence his honeſt labour: and 'tis one of the moſt inglorious things in the world to ſee a a covetous Phyſician, earneſt for Fees, and uſing poor and little art to raiſe the eſteem of his own worth, or ſuggeſt the earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his expectation. In order to which great End he ought to be a a Lover of mankind, as being the chief of Gods mundane Works, of near relation to himſelf; coequal in Gods regard, and this as well from the natural tie which God has implanted, and a due regard of the excellency and admirable frame and texture of mans body, and the extenſive abilities of his mind, as from a ſenſe of that duty which is incumbent upon him, from the time he engaged in the Profeſſion: where, beſides the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations mentioned, he undertakes a Truſt, a Truſt of mighty mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lives of men committed to his care, of which great regard is had as well by the Laws of our Country, as by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared pleaſure of God in his divine inſtitutions. This univerſal Love to his kind, which ſhould be the common bond of Amity, and good will to men, will engage him in the care of particulars: And this I would have more expreſly the eminent mark of our Profeſſion; namely, that Phyſicians are indeed Lovers of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and of all the works of the Creation, as being daily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant in the contemplation of the infinite Wiſdom of God, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted in the never enough to be admired contexture, order, variety ond curioſity of the parrts of the Creation, as likewiſe in imitation as far as his ability extends, of the great Phyſician
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110349:11"/>both of Body and Soul, our bleſſed Saviour, who went about, doing good and healing all that were ſick.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It follows then in the next place, that he ſhould keep his mind in a juſt and even temper, that as it ſhould not be tainted with Covetouſneſs, and low deſires; ſo neither puffed up with Pride or Diſdain; as if his poor and indigent Brother were not a fit object of his care, but too mean and contemptible for his tenderneſs and viſits: a notorious argument of ignorance and ſelf conceit, ſince God eſteems no man as he is rich or poor, high or low, theſe being accidental diſtinctions, and of mans ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, not intrinſeck and conſubſtantial, and 'tis fit that Phyſicians who are Natures Miniſters, and conſequently Gods, ſhould ſee as God ſees, and not be deluded in their underſtandings, by theſe ſlight veils, which crafty and deſigning men have thrown over the face of human nature: yea as a true Servant of our great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and chief Phyſician, he ſhould, with moſt delight, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant among the poor, to compenſate their ſufferings, raiſe their drooping ſpirits, and make them ſome amends for the want they have of the good things of the would, whereof they enjoy ſo ſmall a proportion. 'Tis not our own worth, that procures for us from God, the univerſal Beſtower, theſe various mercies human nature ſtands in need of; but his own frank and diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Goodneſs: in imitation whereof, we ought to make not me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but need the ſubject of our endeavours; to recover loſt inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence or health was the great deſign of our Maſter, who was to that end converſant with Publicans and Sinners: Though there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Practice among the Rich may be more profitable, yet is the helping of the Poor as much our duty, and more, ſince the Rich are every where courted, and their Practice with much at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance, and many little ſtratagems procured, becauſe of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent pay, and a mean diſtruſt of him who has paſt his word for whatſoever ſhall be done for any of his little ones, giving it an equal eſteem, and conſequently no leſs recompence then if done for himſelf. This ought therefore conſcntieiouſly to be performed by Phyſicians, not to acquire ſame, (though that will unavoidab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attend it) but <hi>ex ſenſu officii &amp; beneficii,</hi> from a true ſenſe of duty and a certain recompence of reward: a reward beyond the Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend of Princes, the Fees of the moſt liberal Nobles; <hi>viz.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of mind here, and Gods favour both here and hereafter.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:110349:12"/>
               <p n="3">3. It becomes a Phyſician, to be curteous and pliable to the Sick, to be of eaſy acceſs, ready and willing to give a full hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them and their friends, that ſo he may receive full infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the nature and ſtate of the Diſeaſe: This is both a more certain way and more ſatisfactory to the Sick, than to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fign a Reputation, by being thought able, <hi>uno quaſi intuitu,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to diſcern the quality, difference and accidents of Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, in the Knowledg whereof (it being very eaſy to miſtake, and thoſe miſtakes being of no ſmall conſequence) a Phyſician cannot be too ſagacious and circumſpect An obſervation of ſuch care is no ſmall encouragement to the Sick, and by being ſo, is a conſiderable advantage in the expulſion of a Diſeaſe. To be moroſe and mageſterially concluſive, argues that a Phyſician has more care to pleaſe himſelf then his Patient: that he overweens his own knowledg, that he takes that for certainty, which, at the beſt is but rationall conjecture: aſſiſted by rules of Art not infallible: That he ſhews himſelf more a Maſter than a Phyſician; which is oppoſite to that candor and affability, which are ſet down by the moſt ingenuous who have writ upon this Subject as the characteriſtical note of a true Phyſician<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hippocrates</hi> therefore in his Chapter <hi>de Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dico</hi> has (according to his comprehenſive Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom) moſt excellently adviſed in this particular, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. That a Phyſician be of good and honeſt manners, and that to all he joyn together gravity and humanity, or love to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: for an inconſiderate yielding and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie promptitude, though it ſometimes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, yet is it indeed contemptible: and again, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. As to his Geſture; let him have conſideration and Wiſdom in his Countenance, not aſperity and ſowerneſs, leaſt he appear to be a pleaſer of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and a hater of mankind.</note> That although it may be neceſſary in ſome caſes, to Patients humorous, conceited and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onative of their own knowledg, to be poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and enforce a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance, by overruling arguments, and manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of danger: yet is this but ſeldom, and only to ſuch to be done: no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing being more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and profitable to the Sick than a gentle comportment, joyned with diligence, and real ability, with ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity and unſeined affection. With real ability, I ſay, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned
<pb facs="tcp:110349:12"/>affection: for without theſe to uſe glozing and flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſpeeches, and to ſubſtitute them with hopes to paſs them cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, inſtead of what the Patient expects and his Diſeaſe requires, is a piece of impoſture, no leſs criminal than to cover ignorance with auſteer ſeverity, and to daunt the Patient from conſidering his Phyſicians true worth, by his aſſumed arrogance and conn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent promiſes. In this as in all other the bufineſs of mankind, juſt and ſincere dealing is ever the beſt, moſt ſatisfactory to others, moſt contentful to the Conſciences of thoſe who uſe it, moſt commending a Phyſicians worth and advancing his Practice: For all the little arts that are otherwiſe uſed of obliging, engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiating, or other contrivances of inſinuation, are upon their diſcovery extreamly prejudicial to them who uſe them, and produce a quite contrary effect to what they were deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It becomes a Phyſician as well to bear himſelf with juſt reſpect towards other Phyſicians, as toward the Sick: the only means to to maintain that fair and friendly correſpondence, which ſhould be between Profeſſors of ſo noble a Faculty: and in order to this, Modeſty and Ingenuity are the worthy qualities which have been the grace and ornament of the beſt Phyſicians and by which regular Profeſſors have been diſtinguiſhed from boaſting and vain-glorious Mountebanks: Real worth commends it ſelf, and the frequent benefit the people find by the Counſels of thoſe who are well verſed in their Art, takes off the neceſſity of any other ſtratagems. Boaſting (whatever it is in other Profeſſions) has been always accounted by the beſt able to judg, to be an effect either of weakneſs of mind, joyned, as it often is, with arrogance; of want of real ability, or of little Practice: for where there is modeſty, worth and competent buſineſs, ſuch irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular courſes are declined, and deſpiſed. It is alſo obſervable, that whoever is ſo vain as to cry up himſelf, reſts nor there, but is ſo injurious alſo as to decry and vilifie others They ſteal from others fame to patch up their own: This though they do not always do in open and expreſs terms, leaſt they ſhould be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to account for it, (that being one great end of the Law, that one mans fame may not be at the mercy of another) yet are
<pb facs="tcp:110349:13"/>there many ſly expreſſions uſed, as abuſive and damageable as if they had ſaid it <hi>in terminis;</hi> as, that he could, wiſh he had been ſooner called: That he worders ſuch a courſe was not taken: that he believes all things were intended for the beſt, but it had been well, if ſuch a thing had been done, or ſuch a thing omitted: Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he does well for a young Phyſician, but age and experience is yet wanting, and very neceſſary: Then there are diſlikes without words, as the ſhaking of the head, expreſſing wonder or other paſſion at the relation of what has been done<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> All which, with many more of the like kind, if generally pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſed, would impreſs a greater diſhonour upon Phyſicians, and more certainly ruine the whole Faculty, than all the united en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of all adverſaries whatſoever: For perſons ſo injured, upon a juſt ſenſe, cannot but be ſo true to their own Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as either to take the benefit of Law, where words will bear it, (which however would be of ill fame to the Faculty) or elſe in the like kind retaliate; by means whereof there would ariſe continual revilings and recriminations, by which the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Phyſick would be rend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed to all ingenuous men moſt deteſtable, though, in it ſelf it be, of all others the moſt free, generous and independent, and in fine for mutual candidneſs towards its Profeſſors the moſt deſirable. There are therefore, as I have been informed, ſuch excellent Rules and Statutes, made in the Colledg for the Regulation of the Practice of Phyſick, both with the higheſt regards and greateſt ſincerity, in reference to the Sick, and with the moſt knowing candor and ingenuity to be exerciſed amongſt the Profeſſors thereof, as cannot well be exceeded by the prudence and contrivance of Man with juſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties for the breach &amp; violation thereof the publication whereof; for ſo far as concerns theſe two particulars, would ſurely be very neceſſary, as well for the benefit of the Sick as the infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and ſecurity of all legal Phyſicians; by conſideration whereof, it is to be hoped, that they would all become ſo juſt in their deportment, and ſo regardful of the Reputation of one another, that, by this very candid and juſt demeanour, it ſhould be eaſy for the people to diſtinguiſh a Phyſician regularly bred, eſpecially a Collegiate, from thoſe who are not ſuch, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110349:13"/>are enforced to cry up themſelves, and publiſh their feigne Cures with the exerciſe of many other long practiſed and eaſily diſcoverable impoſtures, only neceſſary, where true worth and legal breeding are wanting. It is further expedient, that he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve thoſe other Rules of ancient Phyſicians, left to us as an inſtance of their Prudence; and eſpecially of the learned <hi>Septae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius:</hi> as that a Phyſician ſhould regard comlineſs and cleanlineſs, which is to the Body as Virtue is to the Mind: A negligent and affected ſlovenlineſs, to be thought it may be ſo earneſtly ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, as to be careleſs of thoſe external things, is as much a ſaulton our hand as ſoftneſs, delicacy, and the being over folici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous by ſpruceneſs and bravery to acquire regard, is a vanity on the other: Thoſe little Politicks are deſpicable, and imply, reconſciouſneſs of defects in real worth, or failer of integrity. No, let it be, ſays <hi>Perſius, — incoctum generoſo pectus honeſto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A mind concoct in noble honeſty, which will carry it beyond all the artifices of inventive man.</p>
               <p>That he boaſts not his own Cures o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Actions, but repreſent all things with Truth, Candor and Integrity, giving every man his due, to the utmoſt, ſparing rather to ſpread his own Fame than that of others; for Practiſe, honeſt, skilful and conſcientious will commend it ſelf, and is the baſis of its own inſeparable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute.</p>
               <p>In converſe, that he be grave, without affectation, ready in his anſwers to give fair and juſt ſatisfaction to all: where conteſts are, to be gentle, yee conſtant for Truth, and reſolute, but with ſtrength of Reaſon, not vehemency of ſpeech: eaſy and affable to all, but of intimate friendſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p with few, and thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect for Prudence and unſpotted Honeſty. Let him ſo modeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly correct the errors of others, as not to have in his regard Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, but Tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h and the good of others.</p>
               <p>That in knowing and taking all fair occaſions of doing good to the Sick he be very perſpicatious which cannot be done but by diligence in Pract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce and making d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yly obſervations, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of the moſt remarkable occurrences.</p>
               <p>That he be not too curions in his diet, hard to be pleaſed, contented with what is wholſome, and in moderation, for he
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110349:14"/>that is too ſolicitous for his Belly, and a Gormondizer, can never ſo ſeriouſly intend his buſineſs, as the weightineſs of the Subject requires. On the other ſide Phyſicians ſhould not be ſordid, greedy of gain, Bargain-makers, Beggars, but frank and liberal, forward to take, at leaſt, equal care of their Patients coming into want, as they uſed to have of them when in plenty: placing their felicity in moderate competency, and the minds content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, rather than in abundance of Wealth.</p>
               <p>That he be patient and watchful over a Diſeaſe, neither ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate in his own opinions, becauſe he as once taken them up, nor too eaſy in yielding to the importunities of the Sick, or their aſſiſtants, againſt the convincing Reaſons of his own mind: but making the health and recovery of the Sick, the true North Pole, guiding all his actions, and preferring it, even beyond his own Reputation, where it may not viciouſly ſuffer, for 'tis in this ſenſe, that according to <hi>Socrates,</hi> we are to conſult our Conſcience rather than Fame.</p>
               <p>Let him be neither moroſe and difficult of ſpeech, nor talkative; in the firſt he offends the Sick, in not giving them that ſatisfaction they may reaſonably expect: In the ſecond he expoſes his own Reputation, and is judg'd inconſiderate, ſudden, not giving juſt time, and ponderation of mind to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf; proceeding tongue and hand before head: which leaves him far ſhort of ſpeaking with that Convincement and Demonſtration, Phyſicians ſhould be always eminent for: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things let him avoid hard and <hi>Latine</hi> Words to his Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, the Guiſe of Empericks and the moſt ignorant Chirurgions: who having no real worth to gain ſolid Reputation by, uſe bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and canting expreſſions, to amuſe their Patients, and to be thought learned: Let this be left to them, whilſt true Phyſicians ſpeak to the Sick and their Aſſiſtants, plainly, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently, and in ſignificant expreſſions, and amongſt themſelves always in <hi>Latine:</hi> which; being brought into Cuſtom, would be inoffenſive, and in which they may more freely expreſs themſelves without diſcouragement to the Sick, and argue mildly and rationally any thing in difference, ſhewing no ſign of diſagreement before the Sick or his Friends.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:110349:14"/>
               <p>He ſhould not be ambitious, there being, indeed, no Honour beyond his Doctorſhip, well put on and worn: others are En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, external Trappings, which the vicious and undeſerving may obtain: But this is real and intrinſeck worth: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore preferrable.</p>
               <p>Vainglorious he is not to be, nor beyond juſt reaſon a ſelf Lover; for by the firſt he excludes himſelf, through ſhame of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thought ignorant, from learning what he knows not: By the ſecond he thinks himſelf arrived to that he is but making a progreſs to, and by overweening his Knowledg, his very imperfect knowledg, for ſuch is that of all mankind, yea of the moſt learned, he gives ſtops and checks to his own Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion.</p>
               <p>Let him keep himſelf entirely the Diſciple of Truth, devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelf to no party, or opinion, by which the Members of a Profeſſion are diſunited, and divide into faction, to the breach of Amity, and miſpending of time, in defence of Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets unadviſedly taken up, and too earneſtly maintained: This is ſpoken in the general, for as to the Collegiate Phyſicians of <hi>England,</hi> it may to their Honour be ſpoken, that thoſe Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings they have produced (which their worth conſidered, are of much more uſe and value than the Rapſodical Volumes of former times, and other Countries) are grounded upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iterated experiments, are new and elaborate, diſengaged from party and faction, induſtriouſly aiming at verity, and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Knowledg, inſomuch that ſcarce any thing that has by them been written; but has found fair acceptance in the world, and very little oppoſition from other men.</p>
               <p>Let him be facile to entertain Conſultations with other Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, and in difficult caſes prompting the Friends of the Sick thereunto; ready to give a fair account of what he has done, that ſo it may appear that nothing has been done indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly or unadviſedly: Let him take care however, that ſuch conſultations be manag'd among Phyſicians themſelves, neither the Apothecaries nor the Friends of the Sick being preſent, that ſo they may proceed with the greater freedom, both of exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning what has been done, and of propoſing what is further
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110349:15"/>to be done, where candor and ingenuity are much to be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the good of the Sick chiefly to be reſpected, and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to that, care is to be had, that nothing be inſiſted upon that is ſuperfluous, meerly for ſhew, or contended for, becauſe of the prerogat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve of ſeniority, or deſire of contradiction: but that according to the method of Conſults, propoſals be rationally urg'd, and candidly admitted, preferring in all things, as I ſaid, the good of the Sick, before any other reſpect or advantage whatſeover.</p>
               <p>He is to be always provided with Medicines to anſwer all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions in whatſoever Diſeaſe, good, ſafe and experimented: nor to judg himſelf a competent Phyſician, until he is furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſuch an <hi>apparatus,</hi> as may obviate all accidents and occurrences, he may in any caſe meet withal. Nor to judg himſelf concerned to conceal any <hi>Arcana</hi>'s, but to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and invite communication, whereby Amity may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, and every one improve each others Knowledg, for the Benefit of the Sick and Advance of the Art: leaving it to Empi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks to boaſt of their ſecret Medicines, which indeed have no other Reputation, but becauſe they are ſecret.</p>
               <p>The beſt Induction into Practice, beſides preparatory Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, Education from youth in thoſe particulars, that are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, as Preliminaries to the Art, is the being brought up under an expert Phyſician: and therefore it is much better, that beginners in Phyſick ſhould betake themſelves to the great Cities, and acquaint themſelves with antient Phyſicians of good note, that they may be guided by them in their Studies, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the Shops of Druggiſts and Apothecaries, ſee the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Hoſpitals, be frequent in Diſſections and conſtant at all publick Anatomies, be admitted to the viſits of the moſt eminent Phyſicians; which courſe is much better, and ſafer for the Sick, than that they ſhould ſettle in little Towns or in the Countrey Villages, and venture upon Practice, upon their own little ſtock of Knowledg, to the great hazard of the Sick, and the improbability of ever gaining good and juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Skill in the Art they profeſs. It is alſo very reaſonable, that, beſides their Univerſity Priviledges, they ſhould ſubmit
<pb facs="tcp:110349:15"/>to the Examen of the Colledg, which enforces them to acquire reaſonable S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill in the whole Body of Phyſick, and gives them the right hand of Fellowſhip with that Honourable Society, and Credit with the People, which though Univerſity men have ſometimes ſtumbled at, yet if they rightly conſider it, they will find their Intereſt therein included, and the Gate of Practice thereby reſerved for them, which otherwiſe would come out, at large, without Order and Regulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>Let him modeſtly bear himſelf in all places he viſits and when his occaſions are with Matrons, or Maidens, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t him ſo manage himſelf and his diſcourſes, as to treat of their Matters with decency in words and actions, that the Profeſſion may thence receive no Scandal nor no ſort of perſons any offence.</p>
               <p>With the unskilful, Nurſes, Women, or others, let him not diſcourſe vainly and impertinently of the Cauſes of Diſeaſes, or of other things not neceſſary for the performance of what is to be done for the Sick; but give them good and plain inſtructions of what each of them are on their part to execute: ſhaming to raiſe a fame by ſuch like little Arts, but by the able and conſciencious performance of their duty in the Cure of the Sick.</p>
               <p>He is very prudently and worthily to bear himſelf in the matter of fees &amp; reward; and therefore he is to make no Compact for the Cure (the mode of ſome Chirurgions and Empiricks) and eſpecially not to make advantage where the caſe is difficult and dangerous; loſing thereby often the opportunities of Cure, not to be recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: They who do ſo, gain to themſelves the name of Sordid, and blem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh the nobleſt Profeſſion Hence is it, that moſt So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties and Colledges of Phyſicians have made By Laws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the way of Compact for Cure, occaſioned, I ſuppoſe, by the many litigations thereupon, to which ſuch Compacts give frequent occaſion. Secondly, Even the ungrateful he is not to leave in their neceſſities, ſince it is better, out of a ſenſe of humanity, to preſerve the ungrateful, than in humanity to leave them through fear of their ingratitude. Thirdly, His allowed Fees he may freely take, and that not with averſation,
<pb facs="tcp:110349:16"/>or bluſhing, as if the obligation were on the fick mens part: If he has done well and honeſtly, he may with confidence receive his reward, ſince it is his Profeſſion and livelihood; to enable h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m whereunto much time and great expence was required: If at any time be refuſes, it ſhould be where he knows neceſſities are, where overmuch liberality is ſhown, or where the caſe is deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: Confident acceptance encourages the Patient, and makes him hope well, that the Phyſician has done his part, which upon ref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l he may be diffident of, ſince he finds the Phyſician ſcarce thinks himſelf worthy of his Fee: whence contempt often fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, and loſs of Fame, although the Phyſician himſelf did it for no ignoble end: To gain Repute and Practice by it, is one of the little Arts ſometimes uſed, but proves to the detriment of the doer, ſince if he continues not ſo to do, and crumbles at ingratitude, he becomes ridiculous and deſerted: But in this particular a latitude is to be left, for the manifeſtation of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip for the recompence of Kindneſſes received; or a deſire upon the ſenſe of worth to lay an obligation.</p>
               <p>'Tis not prudent in a Phyſician to promiſe too much, ſince he cannot promiſe himſelf he ſhall perform it: from his non per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance ariſes two imputations, one of Ignorance that he was ſo miſtaken, the other of, at leaſt, vain arrogance, whereby his future promiſes and prognoſticks will have the leſs credit: Let him manage his buſineſs with Prudence, Skill and good Care, and not to be too poſitive in his Prognoſticks, ſince there is no caſe but is ſo far liable to accidents, as may fruſtrate the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt apparent grounds of a good prediction.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Let not a Phyſician adviſe with too much reſpect to his own cuſtoms, pallat or inclinations: for that is not only empirical, but irrational, and may prove deſtructive: but let him ever have regard to the preſent caſe, with due conſideration of all material circumſtances, of the difference in age, conſtitution, quality, and ſtate of the Diſeaſe, that ſo ſatisfying his own mind, that he does all things rationally, and on juſtifiable grounds (and that alone is to do it <hi>ſecundum artem</hi>) he may be able to ſatisfie others whatever the ſucceſs be, and likewiſe retain a calm and ſerene Conſcience; ſince God Almighty has not allowed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110349:16"/>mankind a certainty of knowledg, or infallibility in <hi>rebus Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicis,</hi> but having given him a rational Soul, with all its facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, whereby he may acquire competent knowledg in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of mans body, as to its conſtitutive and organical parts, the nature of Health, the Diagnoſis and difference of Diſeaſes; and furniſh him likewiſe with a copious <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teria Medica,</hi> to ſupply Medicines that may anſwer all indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations in whatſoever Diſeaſe; it is moſt agreeable to the wiſe conduct of humane affairs, that ſhould not cure Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes by inſtinct, or infuſed knowledg, but uſe his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the beſt manner he can for that ſo noble end, as the Conſervation or Reſtitution of mans Health.</p>
               <p>And thus much concerning the behaviour of a Phyſician, both with regard to himſelf in the ſatisfaction of his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: with reſpect alſo to the Sick, and to other Phyſicians<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> In reference to himſelf, his demeanour is to be virtuous and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> honeſt, to the Sick it is to be with Care, good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Ability: To other Phyſicians with Candor and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity: In the next place I proceed to diſcourſe concerning Apothecaries, in doing whereof, I will conſider the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and various parts of their Art. That it is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſufficient, to take up their time, that medling in any other Profeſſion, eſpecially in giving Phyſick them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, it muſt neceſſarily hinder them from being ſo skilful in their own Art, as they might and ought to be. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing alſo ſhall be ſuperadded of their Deportment in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Sick, to Phyſicians, to the Brethren of their Faculty.</p>
               <p>In our firſt conſideration we will look upon the Art as it is now eſtabliſhed by the Law, In a Fraternity incorporated, allowed certain priviledges, and bearing a proportionable part of the publick charge. No body ever queſtioned, but that this part of the Art was originally in Phyſicians, who, at firſt, made their own Medicines, by the aſſiſtance of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and ſometimes alſo <hi>propriis manibus,</hi> both that they might be aſſured of the well making them, where there was difficulty, as alſo for the pleaſure and contentment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110349:17"/>and that by obſervations made from the proceſs of the work, and many little accidents that would ſometimes inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vene, they might enable themſelves, and collect new Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſms and concluſions. This might properly be ſaid to be in the infancy of the Art of Phyſick, when Knowledg therein was comparatively very little, Intemperance, Luxury and Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes nothing ſo frequent, the buſineſs of Phyſicians but ſmall, and therefore allowing good time for theſe manual opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. But when, in proceſs of time, and by the great pains and endeavours of Learned men, the Science of Phyſick came to be much improved, and in all its parts augmented, Phyſicians, for ſeveral weighty reaſons, did think fit to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt the making of Medicines to a certain number of men in ſome meaſure ſcholaſtically bred, to whom they gave rules, directing the manner and method of each operation, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten inſpecting the performance thereof, that ſo they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves might more intirely intend the anatomical and patho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical part of their Art, and give full time to their Practice and Methods of Curing.</p>
               <p>Now foraſmuch as in the Art thus divided, there is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſufficient to take up the whole time both of the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian and of the Apothecary, and that therefore by ſuch a Diviſion it may well be concluded, that both the buſineſs of the one and of the other, may be the better diſcharged, there is no reaſon, in this particular, to blame the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of our Anceſtors, but rather to approve and applaud the ſame, as a matter of good regard to the Weal of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
               <p>Take we then the Apothecaries Art as thus, aſſigned to a certain number of men incorporated into a Fraternity, with neceſſary and convenient Rules and Orders for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulation and Government of the members thereof, for the prevention and Government of the members thereof, for the prevention of fraudulent and male operations, and it is to be acknowledged to be a very excellent and praiſe-worthy Art, eſpecially if we duely weigh and conſider the ſeveral Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and parts thereof, and in how many particulars the Members thereof ought to be converſant, and well skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:110349:17"/>
               <p>For, firſt of all, he ought to be knowing in all ſorts of, at leaſt, domeſtick Plants, and of the ſeveral parts thereof, the Seeds, Roots, Leaves, Flowers, Sprouts, Barks, Woods, Fruits, Gums, Roſins, concreted and liquid Juices; with all other the appendices to Plants: And in order to this, I ſhall take liberty in this place to adviſe, that whoſoever deſigns his Son to be an Apothecary, he ſhould, beſide writing well, the being a good Arithmetician, and the acquiſition in good meaſure of the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue; he ſhould let him ſpend a good part of his time, <hi>viz.</hi> from twelve to fifteen, in gaining the knowledg of what is above ſpecified, which with a little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and encouragement, be will at theſe years be very apt unto, whereby will be gained not only the preſerving him from more trivial buſineſs, or time-waſting pleaſures, but make him much more deſirable, and with leſs money, by any ingenuous Apothecary and very well prepar'd for that Employment.</p>
               <p>Secondly, An Apothecary is to be very well skilled in the knowledg of all forreign Drugs, the place of their growth, the beſt way of bringing them over, he is to know when they are well cured, genuine, free from all adulteration: to learn all the ways how others adulterate them, that he may diſcover them, and not be impoſed upon: The beſt ways of preſerving them, whether in Boxes, Glaſſes or Pots, and of what mettle. This is a matter of great comprehenſion, the <hi>Materia Medica</hi> being of vaſt extent: and therefore requires much time and great pains.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, He is alſo and which is the choiceſt part of his Art, to underſtand well the way and beſt Methods of making up Medicines as well external as internal, which being of very various ſorts, to keep in a readineſs moſt of which he is obliged: the greateſt part of his time taken up therein, will be but little enough. So that although he be a very ſerious and induſtrious man, and uſed to no extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies of any kind, he ſhall not complain for want of buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, this part of his Art being abundantly competent and copious: the making of all ſorts of diſtilled Waters, ſimple
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:110349:18"/>and compound; of the laſt of which (not to ſay any thing of the firſt, moſt of them being ſuperfluous,) there are in the Diſpenſatory 38 beſides theſe Magiſtrales, which they make either by order of Phyſicians or others 10 Tinctures, 9 medicated Wines, 8 Vinegers, 100 Syrups, 17 compound Honies, 12 Robs or thickned Juices, ſeveral Loochs, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dits, Conſerves and compound Sugars 33 compound Powders, 38 Electuaries and Confections, beſide 24 that are purging, 28 ſort of purging Pills, 3 Opiats, 32 Trochiſes. Abundance of compound Oyls, 29 Unguents ſimple, ſo called, and 20 more compound, 52 Cerats and Emplaiſters: in the making of which (the Ingredients being at ſeveral times of the year ripe, brought over or fit for uſe) there is ſcarce any ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon but, their time is required for one or other part; the former two particulars being once well acquired, are always ready in the mind, by the help of dayly practiſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. But the Medicines of their Shops being daily in decreaſe, or decay, there is a neceſſity of a conſtant ſupply, which requires a conſtant labour and attendance.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Add to all this the Diſpenſing of Medicines, and giving them according to order, injecting of Clyſters, and, as they have now ordered the matter, applying of Lee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, raiſing and dreſſing of Bliſters: Let us conſider all theſe together, and then let any reaſonable man judg whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be not enough to take up the whole time of an Apothecary? whether a man that ſhall be ingeniouſly and induſtriouſly converſant about all theſe, can fail of good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, and be other than very deſireable amongſt men? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch a one can want a good livelihood? and laſtly, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by medling with the buſineſs of a Phyſician, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing Phyſick, he does not draw a perplex'd trouble, and diſquiet of mind upon himſelf; by engaging where he has neither a legal Call nor competent Ability, injuring there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by not only the Phyſician, but the Sick, and his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, if the vain hope of a little profit, and that but imaginary neither, has not made it inſenſible: when eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and of neceſſity, he muſt, by ſo interfering, neglect ſome conſiderable parts of his own Profeſſions, and by his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:110349:18"/>much abſence from home, being engaged with (at he calls them) his Patients, give opportunity to his Servants to be ſlight and negligent in the performance of their duties, and liable to many omiſſions and miſtakes, which might have been prevented by the preſence and overſight of a diligent Maſter: This doubtleſs deſerves a ſerious conſideration, when both Profit and Conſcience are concerned, when by intermedling with what they have no juſt right to, they neglect that duty which is incumbent upon them, and the acquiſition of Skill neceſſary for the diſcharge of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
               <p>As the Apothecaries think it high injuſtice to have their Profeſſion taken from them by others not bred thereunto, or having no lawful authority to uſe their Art: So is it no leſs injury, for them to practiſe Phyſick, thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vading the Profeſſion of Phyſicians, to which they are bred at vaſt charge, long expence of time, and under the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of the Law. In ſo doing, the Apothecaries, beſides the unpleaſantneſs of living out of their Sphear, and the injuſtice towards thoſe Phyſicians that are in being, they hinder, and, in great meaſure, ſhut up that paſſage, which ſhould be kept open for Univerſity men, to plant themſelves either in this or in other Cities, or great Towns of the Kingdom, as the end of their Labours or Studies: This paſſage, I ſay, is ſhut up by practiſing Apothecaries, except it be to ſome very few, whoſe Fame hath gone before them, and uſher'd them into the World: ſo that the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities are no leſs injured than the Colledg here: and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven poſterity, the Succeſſors of both: Upon conſideration of which, if both the Colledg here and the Phyſicians of the Univerſities ſhould reſolve to take the matter of Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy into their own hands, it were but juſt retaliation, who notwithſtanding, out of great Moderation and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, have aim'd at reducing the overflowing ſtreams within their juſt bounds, deſiring much rather, that the Apothecaries ſhould be ſenſible of the exorbitancy, and timely draw back into their proper ſtation, without forc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:110349:19"/>unwilling, perſons to the utmoſt remedy.</p>
               <p>This the Apothecaries excuſe, by urging a neceſſity of ſo doing, leaſt they loſe their Patients: A neceſſity of their own creation, and within the capacity of their own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany to reſtrain. If this neceſſity had been brought upon them by Phyſicians, there would appear ſome ſhew of Juſtice in their Plea: but ſince it is apparently otherwiſe, they have only themſelves to condemn for their tranſgreſſion, and no leſs to accuſe themſelves for the feigning a pretended neceſſity, to ſalve an unlawful Intention, They are ſeriouſly to lay this to heart, and in caſe they ſhall not reſolve upon a Forbearance and Regulation herein, they muſt juſtly blame themſelves for any Reſolutions that may be taken, though never ſo much to the dammage of that Fraternity, for the Remedy thereof. It may he the moſt of that Society may be well reſolved in this particular; but that is not enough; for, if a conſiderable number ſhall perſiſt from the Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs they find therein, in this unlawful practice, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve all the reſt therein, and in what may be ſuffered thereby, and therefore are concerned not only to conform to what is Reaſon themſelves, but to carry it at their Hall againſt the minor number oppoſing, or to proteſt againſt them, that ſo the Colledg may know how to make their Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>Concerning their Deportment, beſides the common Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Honeſty that ought to be in all men; for as <hi>Dodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus</hi> obſerves, <hi>praeſtat virum bonum eſſe Pharmacopoeum quam Socratem,</hi> foraſmuch as the Health and Lives of Men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends very much upon his Skill and Fidelity: he is alſo fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to demean himſelf towards the Sick, with regard al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to Phyſicians, and the Brothers of his Faculty.</p>
               <p>Toward the Sick, firſt, in well preparing their Medicines, according to the Phyſicians order, with good Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, not adulterated, not decayed with age, without ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of one thing for another, at his pleaſure, either for cheapneſs, or his preſent want thereof: In that caſe he ought to look out for it, or if it cannot be had, he is
<pb facs="tcp:110349:19"/>to acquaint the Phyſician therewith, that ſo he who knoweth the reaſon, order and dependency of his own Preſcription, may ſubſtitute what he conceives moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient.</p>
               <p>Secondly, He is to take care; that Medicines be timely made, that they may be given ſeaſonably, according to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, much depending thereupon: beſides that the Sick and their Friends are uſually veay earneſt and ſolicitous for what they judg will be helpful in their diſtreſs, and the Phyſician does place much in the ſeaſonable exhibition of what is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, He is not to interpoſe Medicines of his own, unleſs in a caſe of abſolute neceſſity, where the Phyſician cannot be conſulted; forasmuch as he cannot be aſcertained of the Phyſicians intentions, and may therefore fruſtrate and invalidate what is preſcribed by his interpoſition.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, He is to make a Conſcience in the prices of his Medicine, deſigning his profit to ariſe, not from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercharging any one Patient, but from his gaining of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, by his care and conſcionable dealing towards all. And though in this caſe, ſome reſpects are to be allowed to his Charge, to the greatneſs of that <hi>apparatus</hi> he is required to maintain in his Shop, to the loſs and decay of Medicines, yet all this is to be done, with ſuch prudent regard to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Sick, that, placing his Intereſt in the multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of Patients fairly acquired, he may give none diſtaſt, by ſhewing himſelf covetous of Gain, or craftily dealing with any.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, His Charity to the Sick that are poor is not to be wanting, he will be recompenced for it, in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of his Mind, in the Obligation he lays upon the Poor, which, by reflection, will paſs to the Rich, or if this laſt fails (which he is not to be too ſolicitous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout) he may truſt God Almighty for his Paymaſter, who never fails to recompence good actions, as not to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh evil.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In reference to Phyſicians the Apothecaries ought to
<pb facs="tcp:110349:20"/>be ful of fair and juſt reſpect, foraſmuch as they entruſted to their management, one of the prime and conſiderable parts of their Art: by means whereof the Apothecaries came to be a Company, and to have eſteem and repute in the world: And though they may be apt to urge that the Phyſicians did not do this for the ſake of the Apothecaries, however ſince they reap the profit of it, their Gratitude ſhould oblige them to make a fairer Interpretation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They cannot but know, at leaſt, their experimental ſufferings will make them underſtand, that their Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments depends upon the Credit and Reputation of Phyſicians, and therefore for them to uſe any practices to the diminution thereof, is not only to undermine the Credit of the Art, and of the legal Profeſſors thereof, but therein alſo to ſubvert the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of their own Intereſt. I might here enumerate the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny little Arts, that have to this purpoſe been uſed upon a great miſtake that they do therein better conſult their own Profit, but ſuppoſing that time and experience had made them better to underſtand themſelves, I paſs it over, no proofs or diſcoveries being more convincing than their own ſufferance, which is acknowledged almoſt by them all.</p>
               <p>In the third place I am to mention ſome particulars con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their Deportment one towards another.</p>
               <p>Firſt, It ought to be full of Kindneſs and common Juſtice; and therefore they are to avoid all undue undervaluations and ſupplantings one of another: <hi>Concordiâ res parvae creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt.</hi> If ſome take a liberty to defame the Credit of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, it may be retaliated, and then what will this beget but criminations and recriminations, to the prejudice of the whole: The Rules of common right ſhould ſteer them all, and where diſingenuity tranſgreſſes, the good and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom orders of the Fraternity ſhould take place, and be ſtrictly put into execution. Severity reſtrains Injuries, remiſsneſs gives them encouragement.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Their particular crying up of a Phyſician, on whoſe Practice they deſign to depend, is not only injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to other Phyſicians, but little leſs than a Confederacy
<pb facs="tcp:110349:20"/>againſt their Brethren Apothecaries: It begets Factions in the little Commonwealth of Phyſick, ſince it enforces o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to do the like: beſides the private inſinuations they muſt here uſe, of crying up ſome and decrying others, a very great and injurious licenſe being here often uſed, in their private and ſubtil ſuggeſtions, which redounds alſo to the detriment of one another.</p>
               <p>A third inconvenience is their ſetting too great a rate upon ſuch <hi>Noſtrums</hi> as Phyſicians have placed amongſt ſome of them: By means whereof other Apothecaries, who are by preſcription to provide thoſe Medicines, are forced to charge the Sick with unreaſonable rates, to their great diſcredit, and yet it may be to be no gainers thereby, it may be loſers, or to endanger the loſs of their Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers. This is a conſiderable evil, and is to be rectified, if not by the ingenuity of the Apothecaries, yet by the prudence of Phyſicians, who, for the preventing of ſuch excortions, ought rather to communicate their particular Medicines to ſeveral Apothecaries,</p>
               <p>This ſhall ſuffice to have ſpoken concerning the Demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Apothecaries, to the Sick, to Phyſicians and to their own Fraternity, and it is hoped, that it will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain thoſe good ends for which it was intended, <hi>viz.</hi> the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Sick, and the making of the buiſineſs of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries more comfortable to themſelves, and more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to Mankind.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:110349:21"/>
            <head>Concerning Midwives.</head>
            <p>IT is no ſmall wonder to thoſe who do well conſider it that Midwifery, which is of ſo great concernment to the conſervation of Women, and bringing children into the world, ſhould be under little or no Regulation: and that it is free for any Woman, urg'd by neceſſity, or tempted by profit to undertake ſo weighty an Employment, autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized thereunto by thoſe who have no skill themſelves, and upon the Certificate of half a dozen of goſſiping Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, eaſily admitted upon the weighty motive of five or ſix pounds.</p>
            <p>Hence is it, that many very young, ignorant, unhandy Women, of little or no skill to turn themſelves to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral accidents occurring in that affair, or ability to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce preternatural Scituations of Children when towards the Birth, or to know how to bring them into the world in different poſtures; of very incompetent Knowledg alſo to adviſe Women in the various contingencies of their Labours and Lyings in, are yet permitted to practice that Art, without any previous examination, or any proper courſe taken for furniſhing them with neceſſary Skill, for ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking.</p>
            <p>Hence is it alſo, that the Lives of very many women and children are unobſervably loſt; many women diſabled for futute Conceptions, and rendred ſickly through the whole courſe of their lives, and many Children diſtorted, made obnoxious to Diſeaſes of the Head, the Rickets, and many other weakneſſes: Theſe through their unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs working the Bodies of Women, where there is no occaſion, becauſe they would not be thought igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and on the other hand often neglecting opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110349:21"/>through want of Knowledg what and when to do, whereby ſometimes one, and ſometimes both Mother and Child are very much endangered, or loſt.</p>
            <p>Hence is it likewiſe, that the Man-Midwife is call'd upon on every ſmall occaſion, to the great augmentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Charge, to the infinite diſtaſt of modeſt Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and this either becauſe of the Ignorance of the Midwife, or becauſe ſhe would engage the Man Midwife to give her a good word, and ſpeak well of her amongſt the Women.</p>
            <p>Where<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by the way, it is to be taken notice of, that the Man-Midwives proper buſineſs ought only to be where one or the other is deed, where an Inſtrument and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence is to be uſed, which is an action not agreeable to the ſoftneſs of the female Sex. In all other caſes Midwives ought to underſtand how to behave themſelves, and to deliver Women, and ſo they were in former ages uſed to do, until now there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s grown a kind of Trade, Confederacy and Combination between ſome Midwifes and ſome of the men exerciſing that work.</p>
            <p>Conſidering the whole matter, I thought it expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, to communicate to the World, both the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate of Midwifery, as I have done, and alſo to ſubjoyn a few Propoſals for the better Regulation and Government of that ſo important a Buſineſs.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That two Members of the Colledg of Phyſicians ſhould ſet themſelves apart particularly for Midwifery, and Ute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine Diſeaſes: and that in order thereunto they ſhould, <hi>ab initio,</hi> direct their Studies chiefly to theſe ends.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That no Midwife ſhould be admitted to the Practice of Midwifery until ſhe had firſt ſignified the ſame to the Preſident of the Colledg, and Cenſors, and alſo to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two Phyſicians engag'd in the Practice of that Art; and that a month, at leaſt, before ſhe admits her ſelf to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination: during which time, inquiſition is to be made of her behaviour, her life and converſation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:110349:22"/>
            <p n="3">3. That at a time then to be appointed, ſhe be examined by the ſaid Preſident, Cenſors, and two Fellows, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her fitneſs for ſuch an undertaking, and that likewiſe the Midwife her ſelf, whoſe Deputy ſhe has been, do <hi>viva voce</hi> certifie concerning her being skilful and well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what ſhe deſires to undertake. And that then the Preſident, Cenſors and Fellows, well approving her fitneſs, do authorize her to practiſe the Art of Midwifery, by Letters of Licenſe under the Colledg Seal, the Fees to be but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That no Woman do practiſe the ſaid Art, but ſuch as are in this manner licenſed thereunto, and that upon a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable penalty.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That for the better enabling Midwives to this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, they be permitted to be preſent in the Colledg at the Diſſection of Womens Bodies.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That this be drawn into form by learned Counſel, and added as a ſupplement to the Charter of the Colledg of Phyſicians.</p>
            <p>The Office of Faculties may herein ſomething ſuffer, but 'tis apparently for common good: The forwardneſs of Womens thruſting themſelves, without due fitneſs, reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble skill and preparation, is indeed hereby reſtrained, but that is both juſt and neceſſary: ſince all men will eaſily aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, that a publick benefit is to be preferred before private Commodity and injurious Licence.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:110349:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
